<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bravch's work finished a sermon preached at the funeral of that painful labourer in the Lords vineyard, Mr. James Sharp, and now published at the earnest request of his friends / by Nicholas Blake ...</title>
            <author>Blake, Nicholas, Preacher of the Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12944</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12647462</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12647462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65180</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28334)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65180)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 975:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bravch's work finished a sermon preached at the funeral of that painful labourer in the Lords vineyard, Mr. James Sharp, and now published at the earnest request of his friends / by Nicholas Blake ...</title>
                  <author>Blake, Nicholas, Preacher of the Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sharp, James, 1613-1679.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65180:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65180:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH<hi>'s</hi> Work finiſhed.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED At the FUNERAL of that pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Labourer in the Lords Vineyard, Mr. <hi>JAMES SHARP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed at the earneſt requeſt of his Friends.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nicholas Blake,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>There the wearied are at reſt, <bibl>Job 3.17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:65180:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65180:2"/>
            <head>BAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH<hi>'s</hi> Work finiſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Nehem. III. 20.</bibl>
                  <p>After him Baruch the ſon of Zabbai, earneſtly repaired the other piece, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUR bleſſed Repairer, as he permits the making of breaches on the Walls of his own Jeruſalem, and greater and ſmaller Foxes to enter into his Vineyard; ſo he creates repairers, and ſends whom and when he pleaſeth, allotting to every one of them their particular ſeaſon, work, and talents for repairing of the breaches, or taking the Foxes that ſpoil the Vines with tender Grapes; and particularly obſerves the frame of every one he imploys, what heart they have to work, as <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.6. the people had a mind to work, and how they begin and finiſh their piece of the work; for as he hath ſeveral pieces of work, and ſeveral workmen, ſo he allots to each their ſeveral piece, and indowments ſutable thereunto; and accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and remunerates what they do, and as they do it.</p>
            <p>This Chapter is a ſhort, and yet a long hiſtory, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us an account of the perſons imployed in repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work. Wherein the Lord doth greatly commend all of them, but more eſpecially the repairer in my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65180:3"/>Text, whom you find deſcribed and elegantly ſet forth to you by the Spirit of God in theſe Five Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His name <hi>Baruch,</hi> which is <hi>Benedictus genuflexus,</hi> i.e. a bleſſed and devout man; and indeed as his name, ſo is he, for he was a bleſſed and proſperous repairer, and finiſhed his work, and was moſt obſequious and compliant in his copartner-ſhip with the reſt of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his relation, he is the ſon of <hi>Zabbai, fluxus vel fluens,</hi> pointing out how communicative he was; one conſtantly imparting what he received for the good of others; and this his ſon anſwered in his practice: for as we ſhall hear, he was one that put forth what he had for the good of that work he was called to, or as it is in the Margent, the ſon of <hi>Zaccai,</hi> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth pure and clear, ſuch as indeed our <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Text was, being a man of a pure heart, and of a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning converſation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is deſcribed to us from his work; he repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he vehemently repaired, left not off repairing till all was finiſhed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the manner of his work; he not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, but did it earneſtly, with burning Zeal, and an inflamed heart.</p>
            <p n="5">5. From the nature of the work, it was <hi>Zions</hi> Wall, Church-work; and more particularly, it was ſuch a piece as was allotted him, which he earneſtly repaired, his own part of the Vineyard, his own Watch-Tower; and that to the advantage of all the reſt of the work that other repairers were taken up with; he did not advance his own upon the ruines of others, but with joint harmony, and common advantage finiſhed his work.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65180:3"/>
            <p>The only Doctrine I lay before you from the words, ſhall be this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it's of ſingular commendation, and that which the Lord takes ſpecial notice of, and greatly values, when a Chriſtian or Miniſter does their allotted part of Zions work earnestly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baruch</hi> not only repaired, but did it earneſtly; how earneſt was that other <hi>Baruch,</hi> who was imployed by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to carry the black Rolls that were ſent from God by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> unto the King and Princes of <hi>Judah,</hi> whereof you may read <hi>Jer.</hi> 36. at large; as a moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient ſon of the Prophet he run, and faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged his part in that Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>In the explication of this I ſhall take into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe Five Particulars. 1. The Agent, <hi>Baruch.</hi> 2. The Act, repaired. 3. The manner of this Act, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. 4. The matter about which this Agent was ſo earneſtly imployed. 5. What is in all this that makes it ſo highly commendable, and why the Lord does no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice the ſame.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The Firſt thing is the Agent called out and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in repairing his piece of the wall of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> he run not before he was ſent; he conſulted not with fleſh and blood, being called out to this work. In every inferior Agent there be two things we muſt take into our conſideration. 1. Their excellencies, as qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified by the Maſter-builder for their work. 2. Their weakneſs, as they are men ſubject to many Paſſions and infirmities, by reaſon of the tryals and oppoſitions they meet with in their work.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65180:4"/>
               <p>For the Excellencies of this Agent, I ſhall lay before you theſe Six.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> He had an excellent name, a man of a rare fame, <hi>Baruch</hi> in name and thing. And that 1. In his being bleſſed to others; <hi>Benedictus,</hi> as his name ſignifies, a man, a good man, a Miniſter; an able Miniſter is much, but a bleſſed Miniſter is above all; ſo a repairer, an earneſt repairer is good, but a bleſſed repairer is better, one bleſſed of God with ſucceſs, and made a bleſſing to others, and called by them <hi>Baruch</hi> the bleſſed. 2. In that he was <hi>Baruch</hi> the <hi>genuflexus,</hi> kneeling, devout and reverent in all his addreſſes to the Maſter of the work, of a ſweet yielding and complying ſpirit with the reſt of his fellow-repairers in all things, ſubmitting to the will, and complying with the directions of his Maſter, and condeſcending to them of low degree.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> He was a man of an excellent frame, he had a ſpirit ſuitable to his work, hot and moiſt; hot with a fire of Zeal to have his work finiſhed; and yet moiſt, ſweetly bowing and yielding to the various methods of God about him and his work.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> He was a man of an excellent converſation: For 1. He converſed with the Maſter-builder to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his will and pleaſure, that he might conform all to it. 2. He converſed with fellow-repairers, that he might keep a correſpondence in repairing with the reſt of the repairers. 3. He eyed the end of both, which was to do his work according to the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builders directions, and for the good and advantage of all the reſt of the repairers.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> He was a man excellent in regard of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municativeneſs, in that both he had enough to impart
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65180:4"/>for the good of others, and in that he moſt freely and readily did communicate what he had for upſtirring of them in way of duty, that repairing-work might not be retarded.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly,</hi> He was a man of a publick ſpirit, not only concerned in what was the publick cauſe, but was faithful with the Saints, taking part of their croſs and deſpiſed work of repairing, and in oppoſing the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick defections of the time; he was neither a <hi>Sanballat</hi> nor a <hi>Tobyah,</hi> diſcouraging and drawing off others from the work; but a zealous oppoſer of all ſuch, and earneſt repairer of his piece of the Wall.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6thly,</hi> He was excellent in regard of his activity, he was a very active man, he repaired, and repaired ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly; he was not in this inferiour to that other <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch, Jer.</hi> 36.8. who was ſo active for God, that the Princes ſaid to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> that he was ſtirred up by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch</hi> againſt them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 43.3. <hi>But Baruch the ſon of Neriah, ſetteth thee on againſt us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing we have hinted a little at this <hi>Baruch,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Neriah, Jeremiahs</hi> Scribe, I ſhall gueſs a little at the common weakneſs of Eminent perſons, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently imployed, from what I find obſerved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the ſpirit of God concerning the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>Baruch;</hi> and that upon occaſion of the many va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious tryals that he did meet with in his part of the work, As</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt,</hi> We find he was diſtempered in his expreſſion, a uſual weakneſs in repairers in all ages; you know, <hi>Moſes</hi> in his reſtoring and repairing fell under this, and ſpake unadviſedly. <hi>David</hi> upon the account of his tryals ſpake unbelievingly. <hi>Jonah</hi> paſſionately, and <hi>Baruch, Jer.</hi> 45.3. ſpake not like a valiant man ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65180:5"/>of God or his diſpenſations, but frettingly and as one diſcouraged, <hi>Wo is me now, I am left alone; Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> is impriſoned, and King and Court is againſt me.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> We find he was diſtempered in his heart and affections with immoderate fear and perplexity, like <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah, I do well to be angry even unto death,</hi> when he thought too much of his own croſs, and cryed out, as <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12. Is there any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow? looking on difficulties that were in his way as inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, this made him faint in his ſighing, and remiſs in his zeal and activity for God.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> In that it reached his mind, and did ſo vexand perplex him, that he found no reſt, nor never would, if God had not obſerved his diſtemper, and ſent him a Cure by the hand of <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> even ſo Eminent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments imployed in repairing work, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Excellencies, they may be much diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in their minds, ſo that for ſome time they can find no reſt.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> Such may be the diſtemper, that it may reach their Prayer, and put them upon ſeeking great things for themſelves; as <hi>Baruch</hi> was charged with this, ſo others may be guilty of the ſame: And that 1. As <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch</hi> had a great deſire to be excuſed from the publick noiſe of the Court, and that for his own greater quiet, and ſelf-eaſe; ſo other repairers may be guilty of the ſame weakneſs, eſpecially when they ſeek more of this for themſelves than comes to their lot: this was a branch of <hi>Baruchs</hi> ſeeking of great things to himſelf, and may be alſo found in others not inferior unto him. 2. As he, ſo may other repairers ſeek too great things for themſelves, when they peremptorily ſeek to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65180:5"/>faithful to God in the truſt he hath put them in; and yet to have the favour and countenance of great men, who are no great friends to repairing-work; it's never good when Eminent Inſtruments ſeek to pleaſe both parties, and cannot bear up againſt the frowns of great men. 3. It is a weakneſs, when perſons imployed in repairing-workſeek to be exempted from any croſs or tentation that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to men, eſpecially when they ſee better than themſelves not excuſed from it; <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was Impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Baruch</hi> had no will to come under the like lot, though he knew that ſuffering was the Maſters lot; and to deſire to be freed from this, was very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the general calamities of the day, wherein God threatned to pluck up that he had planted, and to pull down that he had built up.</p>
               <p>The Second thing to be taken into conſideration is the Action, what this Agent did, wherein he was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; the Text tells us, in repairing his piece, he had a particular piece of the work allotted for his ſhare; he had his appointed time wherein he was ſent out to do it, and ſuitable furniture which he ſpends in repairing: which that you may know, I ſhall conſider the original word, which is very Emphatick, and ſeems to branch out his work in theſe Eight Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt,</hi> In that he ſo repaired, as one that was natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned in the work; it was eaſie and pleaſant to him, his reſt and refuge was in his work. <hi>Paul</hi> could not commend <hi>Timothy</hi> more by any thing than by this, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.20, <hi>For I have no man like minded, who will naturally care for the things of your ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> He not only repaired, but did it affectionately, he ſtirred up himſelf and others to the work; he did
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65180:6"/>what he could to raiſe his own ſpirit, and to provoke others to the higheſt pitch of activity in, and about ſo good a work. The word fignifies to kindle or inflame, he inflamed all he could reach, and was ſtill more and more rouzing up himſelf; he ſtirred up his own gift, and did what he could to provoke others to zeal and good works.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> He ſo repaired as to re-edifie, and re-build what had been formerly built, but thrown down by the Foxes and Wild-Boars that came up upon his part of the Wall; he built and re-built without wearying; he did the ſame work over again, and repaired upon occaſion of breaches in his Wall.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> He ſo repaired, that he reformed and did mend what was amiſs; he was not only careful to repair breaches, to prevent ruine, but to remove deformities that would marr the Beauty of his piece of the Wall, that ſo there might not only be a Sanctuary for ſtrength and ſafety, but an Ornament for Beauty and Majeſty.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly,</hi> He ſo repaired as to ſtrengthen; he fortified his piece, he made ſtrong work; as he himſelf was ſtrong for labour, ſo he in repairing his piece of the Wall, not only made ſtrong and firm work, but did thereby ſtrengthen all the reſt of repairing-work done by others; he did not build upon other mens ruins, nor did he weaken their piece of the Wall to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his own, but in repairing his piece was ſingularly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial and ſtrengthning to all the diſtinct parts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing works, and to perſons repairing.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6thly,</hi> The word implies that he was no Lingerer or Loiterer about his work; he haſtned his piece of the Wall; Zeal to the houſe made him quicken his motions;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65180:6"/>he knew his work, he conſidered his wages, and how pleaſant quick diſpatch was to the Maſter, and how commendable, wherever it is; and therefore he made haſte, and delayed not to have his piece of the Wall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7thly,</hi> He was ſuch a repairer as uſed and put forth a holy violence in repairing; he burſted forth, and this he did either againſt himſelf, in caſe he fell heavy and dull at work, by which means this work was not finiſhed; a grievous thing to him, or elſe againſt others, who either had left off the work, or advanced ſlowly in it; who were repairers, but not ſo earneſt as the work called for.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8thly,</hi> He repaired, and continued his work till he had finiſhed; as zealouſly he began, ſo zealouſly he did finiſh his piece, his laſt works were as good as his firſt, his ſtrength was not abated in the way, his fervency and diligence laid the laſt ſtone in his piece, without being either abated or leſſened. Thus much of this Agent and of his Act, He repaired, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Third thing to be conſidered, is the manner of his performance, how he repaired. This the Text tells us, that he did it earneſtly, <hi>flagrante animo,</hi> with a mind ſet on fire by love and zeal to the work. I ſhall only take notice of theſe Four from the manner. And</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt,</hi> He repaired earneſtly, that is, he was intent upon it, and did it with much intentneſs and greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, longing to have all finiſhed: what unwearied continuance was there in this man? ſtill looking to the end, and haſtning to come at it.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65180:7"/>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> He repaired earneſtly, that is, though his mind was ſet upon the end, yet he carefully uſed the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per means to bring things to an Iſſue to their expected and deſired end; he makes fools haſte, that being intent on the end, either neglects the moſt promiſing means, or goes the wrong way to bring him to his deſired and much long'd for end.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> He earneſtly repaired, that is, did moſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately obſerve what did moſt further, or retard his work; he took notice how the Wall went up, and what did moſt advance it, and ſurely made moſt uſe of that which was moſt helpful to the deſign; and did greatly rejoyce to ſee every thing going up and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> He earneſtly repaired, that is, he took great care to have every thing taken out of the way, that let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or hindered the going up of his part of the Wall, and did manfully oppoſe who ever offered to come up to hinder the going up of his piece of the Wall.</p>
               <p>The Fourth thing to be conſidered in my Text, is the ſubject matter, about what this Agent put forth his act in ſuch a manner, and that was the <hi>Mount Zion</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Wall whereof had been broken down, and now a little reviving being granted in the midſt of their bondage, the worthieſt among them fall upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing work; which either was in the Mountain, and ſo was work on <hi>Zion</hi> directly; or it was to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that is, ſuch work as every way tended to the good of the Mountain. It was either Church-work in it ſelf, or conſequentially and reductively it was for the welfare of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> either proximately or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motely; he was either digging or ſowing, or mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65180:7"/>repairing the breach in the Wall: he was as <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribes true Miniſters, one that could do nothing againſt the Truth, or Church of God, but for it.</p>
               <p>But in the Fifth place, it may be required, Why does our Lord ſo much notice, and record ſuch of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants as have done their part of <hi>Zions</hi> work ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Reaſon 1.</label> That his <hi>Baruchs</hi> may be had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6. <hi>the righteous ſhall be in everlaſting remembrance.</hi> And <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.13. <hi>Whereſoever this Goſpel ſhall be preached in the whole world, there ſhall alſo this that this woman hath done, be told for a memorial of her.</hi> God not only remembers his <hi>Noahs,</hi> and cauſeth the waters of their afflictions here abate, but he will have them remembred, eſpecially ſuch of them as have been ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repairers of <hi>Zions</hi> breaches, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.12. <hi>and thou ſhalt be called the repairer of the breach, the reſtorer of the paths to dwell in;</hi> and as the memory of the wicked is curſed, ſo the memory of the juſt is bleſſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7. The name of the wicked ſhall rot, when the name of the juſt ſhall be as an Ointment poured forth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Reaſon 2.</label> Our Lord records his repairers that do their work earneſtly, that thereby he may give proof and teſtimony of his love and reſpect to <hi>Zion,</hi> when he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeth and commendeth thoſe that take delight in her duſt, and imploy themſelves earneſtly in repairing her breaches; he is ſaid to love <hi>Zion</hi> more than all the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of <hi>Jacob;</hi> here is my reſt, ſaith the Lord, here I take delight to dwell; and if ſo, what wonder if he record and commend the man who is the repairer and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65180:8"/>reſtorer of paths to dwell in, that he may have a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pleaſe him?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Reaſon 3.</label> Satan and his Inſtruments notice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſuch to defame, and oppoſe them; what mean theſe feeble <hi>Jews?</hi> will they build up all in one day? if a Fox come up, will he not caſt down their ſtone-Wall? So that ſuch repairers have need of encouragement, and therefore the eyes of their Maſter is upon them for good, his hand with them as with the Apoſtles; he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears for their glory, when oppoſers ſhall be aſhamed and confounded; and when they have done their work, not only gives them their wages, but commends them, <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervants;</hi> and records them in his book of remembrance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Reaſon 4.</label> Our Lord does this, that he may encourage after Ages to be worthy <hi>Baruchs</hi> in their day, repairing their piece earneſtly, notwithſtanding of difficulties, oppoſitions and manifold tentations; that ye be not ſlothful, but followers of them who through faith and patience have inherited the promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.15. we muſt be followers of ſuch as dear children; our great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairer, our bleſſed Jeſus is, and ſhould ever be a pattern to us; inferior builders ſhould be imitated alſo. You know the patience of <hi>Job,</hi> and you have ſeen the end of the Lord; <hi>David</hi> told <hi>Solomon,</hi> I have done ſo much, my ſon; you muſt riſe and be doing, and the Lord ſhall be with you; you ſhall have the Maſters eye of direction and inſpection; you ſhall have his good word; men may have an evil eye upon you, and will ſpeak reproachfully of you, and your work; may call you ſingular, hot-headed, furious and inconſiderate; but God gives thee another,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65180:8"/>and far better teſttimony, and calls it a doing of thy work earneſtly; and thus commends it in <hi>Baruch,</hi> that he may recommend the like practice to thee, to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I come now to the Tranſcript of my Text, which though in every particular it be not ſo full and fair as the Copy, yet ſuch it is as deſerves our obſervation, commendation, and imitation; if it runs not parallel with it, it may be hoped that it comes not far ſhort; and that <hi>Baruch</hi> in my Text, is not much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in all reſpects, than our <hi>Baruch,</hi> who is now fallen aſleep, having finiſhed his generation-work; and who being dead, yet ſpeaketh in ſo many living ſtones as he helped to build in <hi>Zion:</hi> thus repairing his piece of the Wall earneſtly.</p>
               <p>I ſhall uſe neither flattering ſtiles, nor cover his Paul with Hyperbolizing Elogies; but ſtate the compariſon, and ſet perſon againſt perſon, face againſt face, frame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt frame, work againſt work, the Copy and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, and leave you to judg of the likeneſs, and how conform our <hi>Baruch</hi> is to the <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Text, who were beſt acquainted with our dear Brother, and who now have heard of this repairer in my Text.</p>
               <p>That I may methodically emblazon, and ſhew forth the virtues wherewith this Saint and ſervant of the moſt high God (who now hath taken the Kingdom, and is poſſeſſed of it for ever and ever) was qualified for repairing his piece of the Wall, and dreſſing that part of the Vineyard whereof the Holy Ghoſt made him an Overſeer; I ſhall follow the method laid before you in the explication of my Text.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65180:9"/>
               <p>And theeefore Firſt, Let us conſider theſe perſonal Excellencies that were full and fair in the Copy, and were in their due meaſure in the Tranſcript.</p>
               <p>As Firſt, His Name and Fame, there being ſo much Air in this, and it being that which ofttimes meets with contrary blaſts, and foul Air; as I cannot ſay, that it was never tainted by looſe tongues, ſo I cannot ſay that he was never reproached, or that he was a man that all men ſpake well of; for then he had not been honoured with that eminent piece of his Maſters Croſs, which was to be evil ſpoken of; had been without this part of conformity to him, and might have feared that wo, <hi>Wo to you when all men ſpeak well of you;</hi> and doubted much whether that bleſſing belong'd to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Bleſſed are you when men ſhall revile you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my names ſake.</hi> But this I may ſay, that he was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and a labouring one, that needed not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his work, a repairer like the <hi>Baruch</hi> in my Text: <hi>Benedictus,</hi> a bleſſed Miniſter, bleſſed with much work, great ſupplies of ſtrength in the diſcharge of it, and with no ſmall ſucceſs, that makes the labourers work ſweet and comfortable to him; and while I call him a ſervant, and a bleſſed ſervant, I tell you that God gave him a name better than the name of ſons and daughters, and that is, to be a ſpiritual father unto many of you. And as he was bleſſed of God to be uſeful; ſo in the Second place, He may be called <hi>genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexus,</hi> kneeling, devout and reverent in his applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his Maſter, in your name, ſweetly ſubmitting all to the will of God; ſo of a yielding and conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending ſpirit to you, to all men, becoming all things, that he might gain ſome.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65180:9"/>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> As his name was bleſſed, and bowing, ſo his frame was not inferior to our <hi>Baruchs</hi> in the Text: hot and moiſt, hot and zealous for God, and the City of his God, and in oppoſing every thing contrary to God; ſo moiſt and tender; tender-heartedneſs is the beſt frame for a Chriſtian in a time of abounding ſin, and threatned judgments: He often wiſhed a head as a fountain of Tears, and Doves eyes always watring; and who knows but that the Lord hath removed him from the evil to come, becauſe his heart was tender, as 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.19. and it was no ſtrange thing to find it ſo, for that warming influence that heated his heart, melted it down, and made a moiſtneſs in the eye, by which it came to paſs that as Comforts, Croſſes, Words, and Works of God made an eaſie impreſſion on his moiſt and tender heart; ſo this ſame made him more eaſily bow to the Yoke of Chriſt, and the many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markble afflictions he met with in the courſe of his Pilgrimage.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> As <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Text was of a ſhining con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Tranſcript (humane frailties being excepted) did riſe and ſhine after many clouds had paſſed over him. There are three things that commends a mans converſation. <hi>1ſt,</hi> The perſons with whom he converſeth. <hi>2dly,</hi> The matter about which. <hi>3dly,</hi> The end of his converſation. For the perſons with whom the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. tells us with whom we ſhould converſe, <hi>Truly our converſation is with the father and with the ſon.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> tells us that <hi>our converſation ſhould be in Heaven,</hi> from whence we expect our Saviour:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65180:10"/>And I doubt not but this is the conſtant care and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all faithful Miniſters, and was of this our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in particular, if we may judg of this from the conſideration of the perſons he converſed with here below, <hi>viz.</hi> the excellent ones wherein was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of his delight; and as for the matter about which it was, if you look above, it was either to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to a conformity to him, by walking with him, or to recieve from him grace for grace, out of his fulneſs; or if you look below, then it was either to make ſuch as are bad good, or ſuch as are good better; either to bring ſinners to a Saviour, or to confirm them in him. And Laſtly, As for the end of his converſation, the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and principal end, was the glory of his God and Maſter: the ſubordinate, the ſalvation of his own ſoul, and of thoſe that heard him.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> As <hi>Baruch</hi> in my Text was fluent and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative, for what he got, that he laid out on repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his piece; ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> did not only ask rain in the time of the latter, but came down upon you as the rain, delivering to you what he received of the Lord, both word and Sacraments, for redreſſing and repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of you; and ſo preſſing and urgent was he, that he ſeemed as one that would not admit of a delay, much leſs a denial at your hand; and if your heart had been as his, you would have given the hand to the Lord, and come up to his Chariot, which is all Paved with love for the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. That as <hi>Baruch</hi> in my Text was a faithful man in the houſe of God, and in that particular truſt that was committed to him, oppoſing every courſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65180:10"/>that made againſt <hi>Zion;</hi> ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> was no leſs faithful; he not only chuſed affliction with the people of God, but zealouſly contended for the truth, and oppoſed every courſe of defection in his day. I need not tell you what oppoſition he and others met with not long ſince, when armed Forces ſet themſelves to batter down the ſeveral pieces of our Wall: I was then his Neighbour, and cannot forget how the Archers did ſhoot at him; and how notwithſtanding, his Bow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in its ſtrength, and made him, and many more faithful and valiant in that day; the beginning of your reviving, and his witneſſing for you, and of his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous return to you, which he hath increaſed to this day, giving you daily liberty out of bonds, and meat out of the eaters, and made more diſcernable now to his praiſe, and our comfort. Lord grant that our ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude cauſe us not to be ſent back again to a darker Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon.</p>
               <p n="6">6. As <hi>Baruch</hi> in my Text was a very active man, and repaired earneſtly his part; ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> was no leſs active in his ſphere; there is no time ſince he was ſent forth to repairing-work, wherein his activity on all occaſions did not appear; not only doing what he could amongſt his proper Flock, preaching, cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, viſiting the ſick; in a word, in labours as much as any. But if ye will look to his occaſional work, his labour therein was not ſmall, which his abounding compaſſion to the Souls of notorious Malefactors prompted him to. Beſides what moſt of you know in the laſt ſtage of his race, wherein he run as one that reſolved not to reſt till he had all finiſhed. This made him graſp in ſo much work as his day was capable of,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65180:11"/>and made him aſſiduous daily in teaching the younger ſort.</p>
               <p>And leſt you ſhould think that we only blazon his Virtues and Excellencies, I ſhall therefore compare his weakneſſes with that other <hi>Baruch</hi> the ſon of <hi>Neriah,</hi> a worthy man, indued with all the excellencies of the other; and who yet through manifold tentations fell under a diſtemper that would have ſpoilt him, if God had not cured it by <hi>Jeremiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt, As manifold and long Trials run <hi>Baruch</hi> the ſon of <hi>Neriah</hi> into a high diſtemper in his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and made him cry out, <hi>Wo is me now,</hi> Jer. 45.3. So this our <hi>Baruch</hi> by reaſon of his, was ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſled upon by them, as to be diſordered in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, making him ſpeak faintingly and diſcouraged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Wo is me now; eſpecially that his laſt trial moſt to be lamented, conſidering that it did ariſe from them not only of his own houſe, but of his own bowels, which no queſtion did aggravate his trial, as it did the Maſter's, <hi>My own familiar friends,</hi> Pſal. 38. <hi>Judas</hi> was the betrayer of him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As this diſtemper diſcovered it ſelf in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, ſo likewiſe in his heart and affection, and made him faint in his ſighing; ſuch waters coming into the ſoul are bitter, and oft-times overwhelms the ſpirit; and then weakneſſes appears, <hi>viz.</hi> fainting in his ſighing, courage failing, and deſpondency prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This diſtemper ſeized the mind of the one and of the other; ſo that as the one could find no reſt, ſo no more could the other; ſoul and bones vexed, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. till he came to this which you ſee, <hi>where the wearied are at reſt, and the wicked ceaſe from troubling.</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65180:11"/>The Lord ſave you from being ſuch troublers of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters, leſt when you ceaſe to trouble them, you be troubled.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This diſtemper affected the grace of prayer in both; and that as the one did ſeek great things for himſelf, which would not have been ſo great, but with reſpect to the time wherein God was threatning to pluck up what he had planted; ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> and many more might be guilty of that at ſuch a time; and leſt I ſhould be miſtaken, as if I intended worſe than the Copy, I ſhall lay before you the three great things that both might be ſuppoſed to ſeek after.</p>
               <p>As firſt, This was <hi>Baruch</hi>'s infirmity, in that being wearied and toſſed with publick buſineſs, he did too peremptorily deſire-freedom and exemption from this noiſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf groaned under this, and ſaid, <hi>Have I born this people, that all the trouble of them lyes upon me?</hi> Which was the occaſion of Gods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Spirit from him, and giving it to others. So it might be the great thing that our <hi>Baruch</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to be freed from the noiſe he met with in his work, that occaſioned ſome remarkable changes in his pilgrimage, that I in love not only cover, but apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize for by what is ſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This was <hi>Baruch</hi>'s infirmity, in that he was too ſollicitous about the countenance and favour of great men that were no great friends to the Truth; and it was too much for him to ſeek this, when their faces were ſet againſt God. So it may be ſome of you will be ready to ſay, that our <hi>Baruch</hi> was weak in this, that he ſought very much to do his duty faithfully to God, and yet ſo as to pleaſe all parties, which put him on ſome things which a prejudged perſon may be ready
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65180:12"/>to remember, looking over all the excellencies that were in him; but if ſuch as <hi>Baruch</hi> may be thus far prevail'd on by tentations, let us take heed leſt we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be tempted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was too great a thing in <hi>Baruch,</hi> and ſpoke out his weakneſs, in that he ſought ſo much to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and exempted from ſome particular croſſes that better than he had met with, and were lying under, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s impriſonment. So this might be the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our <hi>Baruch,</hi> too peremptorily to deſire to be excuſed from that croſs which in all appearance did ſo much cruſh him, who had run with the horſe-men under other trials.</p>
               <p>I come now in the third place, to take a view of both in their Work, and to ſet Work againſt Work; <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Text repaired his piece of the Wall; and ſo did ours.</p>
               <p>And firſt, Our <hi>Baruch</hi> not only repaired, but ſtirred up the gift of God that was in him, that he might do his work the better; and did what he could to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke others to zeal and good works: the beſt confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this, will be your zealous up-ſtirring of your ſelves, and provoking one another to follow this Copy that he hath laid before you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As he in the Text did repair and rebuild; ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> made it his buſineſs to re-edifie what was at any time broken down, both in doing the ſame things, and repairing the ſame piece of the Wall again, that he might repair the breach. As his work was to quicken ſuch as were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, ſo to reſtore ſuch to life as through ſecurity and untender walking
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65180:12"/>had loſt much of what they had; and the little that remained, in a readineſs to dye.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Text did not only repair brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but reformed what was amiſs in the work, what marred the beauty of the Building; ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> not only made it his work to bring you into a faſe ſtate, but did what he could to make you riſe and ſhine, ſeeing your light was come, and the glory of the Lord riſen upon you.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Text ſo repaired as to ſtreng-then; he not only did work, and ſtrong work, as to his own piece; but did ſtrengthen the hands of other Repairers: ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> not only laboured to ſtreng-then the feeble of his own flock, and to make the fearful heart ſtrong, but did what he could to ſtreng-then that piece that belonged to other repairers, by his frequent Lecturing in ſeveral places.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As he in the Text was no lingerer; ſo our <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch:</hi> no ſooner was he ſent, but he run; he had the Hinds foot; did not linger long; a labourer, no loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer; as a man fit for his Maſters uſe, and prepared for every good work; as one newly come up from the waſhing, bearing Twins, a noble deſign for the glory of God, and for the ſalvation of the ſouls of others; as one winged with faith and hope, with love and longing to have all finiſhed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He was ſuch a Repairer as did his work with a holy violence, knowing that the ſtrong man was not eaſily caſt out, and that the kingdom could not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken but by force; and that either againſt himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had not finiſhed his work; or againſt others, who either had laid by their work, or advanced ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in it.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65180:13"/>
               <p n="7">7. As <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Copy continued at work till all was finiſhed, and did not give way to diſcouragements, to cauſe him ceaſe from the work; ſo our <hi>Baruch</hi> in the Tranſcript, did not only continue, notwithſtanding of all diſcouragements to take him off from it, but his laſt works were his beſt works, ſowing in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and at Evening not with-holding his hand, not knowing whether this or that ſhould proſper.</p>
               <p>And if to all this, in the <hi>4th</hi> place, you will conſider, and compare the manner of their repairing; you will find a ſweet ſemblance between the one and the other.</p>
               <p>And 1. As he in my Text earneſtly repaired, that is, naturally, ſo our <hi>Baruch,</hi> naturally did that which he did in repairing his piece; his mind was ſo bent upon his work, and delighted in it, that he naturally cared for the things of your ſoul. I may ſay in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, it was his meat and drink to do his Fathers will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He repaired earneſtly, that is, with great ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and affection, great intentneſs of mind, ſtill looking and longing to have all finiſhed, which in part may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his engaging himſelf in ſo much work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He repaired earneſtly, that is, he conſcientiouſly uſed all appointed means conducing to his expected and longed for end; he imployed himſelf both about foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and ſuperſtructuary-work, plowing and planting, watching and watering old and young, looking up to Heaven for the increaſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He repaired earneſtly, that is, he narrowly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved how things proſpered, and grace did grow, and endeavoured neither to <hi>break the bruiſed reed,</hi> nor <hi>quench
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65180:13"/>the ſmoaking flax;</hi> neither to over-drive what was with young, nor refuſed the Lambs a place in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He repaired earneſtly, that is, he zealouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the truth when it was invaded on his piece of the Wall, according to his ability, and humbly call'd in the help of others, when Foxes greater and ſmaller were too many for him; and daily laboured to have that taken out of the way that hindered the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs grouth, and inlargment of his building.</p>
               <p>And in fine, if you will conſider that the ſubject matter was <hi>Zion,</hi> or work about <hi>Zion,</hi> either Church-work directly, or that which tended thereunto, as his educating of the youth; for he was either in his Church as a Paſtor, feeding them; or in his School as a Maſter, hewing them that they might be fit ſtones for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of breaches; leading on his people as a flock, in a ſtorm, to a place where they may reſt at Noon; and leading them into the banquet of Wine for repaſt. I ſay, if you will put all theſe together, and conſider them, you will ſind a Tranſcript very like the Copy in my Text, and ſo one worthy to be commended for our imitation, and remembred with joy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And now as by this compariſon, I have given you a juſt and charitable account of him who is gone, ſo I would alſo give you the particular improvement of all.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, Seeing a Miniſter, and a bleſſed Miniſter, who repaired his part of the Wall earneſtly, is fallen aſleep, can we behold this, or hear of it, who are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and not hear this ſpeaking aloud to us, at leaſt for my ſelf, who am the leaſt of all Saints, to whom
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65180:14"/>this Grace is given to Preach the inſearchable riches of Chriſt: I cannot but hear both the Copy and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript preſſing me to follow the Copy in the Text, and to de cautious, leſt theſe weakneſſes be found in me that were found in others. We have been at much pains to attain the name of able Miniſters; but that which is better, is to be a bleſſed Miniſter; bleſſed our ſelves, and a bleſſing to others. It may be feared, that many in our day are ſent to make ears heavy, and hearts fat, till all be deſtroyed: we muſt obey Gods call, it's true; but is it not more comfortable to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in healing of the Nations, and bleſſed with good ſucceſs in our work? Doth not this call us to look to our frame, and ſee whether we be zealous for the Lord of Hoſts; whether we be fire, or dow in our up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſide in our acting for God; and whether we be of a tender heart, mourning for all our own and the ſins of others: we reprove many ſins that we never mourn over: may not ſome of us ſay, <hi>My moiſter is turned to the drouth of ſummer.</hi> Are our converſations like the Copy? do we converſe with the Father and the Son, and that for the obtaining grace for grace, to the end, that our Lord may be glorified, and ſouls ſaved in the day of the Lord? ſhould we not ſtudy to receive more, and to be more liberal in our deviſings for God, and in communicating whatever we recieve to them? he ſends it without reſpect of perſons. Ought not we courageouſly oppoſe the defections of the time, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when we ſee whether all this tends: namely, the depriving of us, and our poſterity of the Goſpel? will it be comfortable to ſome called Miniſters to know at laſt, that they were made the ſcourge for vexing of the true Martyrs, that earneſtly have, and would repair
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65180:14"/>their piece? or that they have given way to a <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballat</hi> and a <hi>Tobya</hi> to inhance the whole work of the repairers, who yet put not forth their hand to the Work, except it be to build hay and ſtubble on the precious foundation, that out of this there may a fire break out to make deſolate <hi>Zion</hi>'s Palaces. O where is the man that rules with God, and is faithful with the Saints in our day! Let neither their full cup, nor the work of them that turn aſide, cleave unto us.</p>
               <p>Can we read the Copy, and not ſee that it calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to be more active for God, ſtirring up that gift that is in us, provoking others to love and good works? It's true the enemy ſows his tares, caſts down what we built up; but ſhould not we rebuild all again, that breaches may be repaired? Let us not think it enough to get our people brought in to a ſafe ſtate, but to a ſhining converſation, that beauty and ſtrength may be the two pillars in our little ſanctuary, in our burning buſh, yet not conſumed. Our Enemy is ſwift as the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, ſuch as turn aſide as the ſwift Dromedary. Let us neither be ſlow in heart to believe, nor in hand to work. Let us uſe a holy violence, and chuſe rather to endure hardneſs, to pleaſe our Maſter, than to indulge our fleſh. Let us go on till we finiſh, with that ſame fervency and burning zeal againſt all oppoſers, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent love towards all the lovers of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, keeping cloſe to our piece of the Wall, doing what we can to ſtrengthen the hands of one another: ſo ſhall we be <hi>Baruch</hi>'s recorded and remunerat, when our Lord comes to make up his Jewels, as theſe who have repaired our part of the Wall earneſtly, and find that the Spirit of our <hi>Elias</hi> reſts upon us.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65180:15"/>
               <p>And does not this likewiſe ſpeak words of caution to us? We have fallen in a tempting place of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; we are in perils every where; let us beware that none of theſe things move us either to ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly with <hi>Moſes,</hi> unbelievingly with <hi>David,</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately with <hi>Jonah,</hi> or diſcouragedly with <hi>Baruch, Wo is me now.</hi> We ſhould beware that we abate not our courage; we ſhall reap if we faint not; to ſigh for the abominations of the time, is our duty, and to go between the porch and the altar weeping and praying, <hi>Spare thy people;</hi> but to faint in our ſighing, neither ſuits our Cauſe nor our Leader and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who is for us, be where he will, and while he hides, and will return to us again, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.10.</p>
               <p>We ſhould beware that our minds be not diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; it's a part of <hi>Zion</hi> her ſong, after the Lord hath opened her gates, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.34. That he will keep them in perfect peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who can be ſtill, knowing that he is God? If we cannot reſt in our minds in the day of trouble, let us beware of ſelf-ſeeking in ſuch a day, or ſeeking great exemptions and priviledges for our ſelves. Let us be content with our allotted Croſs, for he hath ſaid it, <hi>I will never leave you nor forſake you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place I addreſs my ſelf unto you who were the flock of his paſture, and the ſheep of his hand. Certainly this matter belongs to you in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner. What the young prophets ſaid to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> that would I ſay unto you, 2 King. 2.5. <hi>Know ye not that the Lord hath taken away your Miniſter from your head to day,</hi> both in the midſt of his work, in midſt of his days, and in the greatneſs of his ſtrength? I have but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65180:15"/>three words to ſpeak unto, as the voice of this rod, and of him who hath appointed it.</p>
               <p>The firſt is a word of <hi>Lamentation;</hi> and that 1. in remembrance of this, that when he wept over you, conſidering the miſery many of you was under, and the hazard you were in of loſing your immortal ſouls, you then rejoyced. What was ſaid of <hi>Judah,</hi> may be ſaid of many this day, <hi>When thou didſt evil, then thou rejoyceſt,</hi> Jer. 11.15. As our Lord Jeſus wept over <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> when the people did all rejoyce; ſo it is with his ſervants, that they are left by their people to mourn alone, and to pray alone, while they with <hi>Iſrael</hi> are dancing about their golden calves: You laught, but your Miniſter wept, conſidering how little you knew of theſe things that belongs to your peace. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be afflicted, and mourn and weep now; let your laughter be turned unto mourning, and your joy to heavineſs, if you would have the Lord lift you up in due time. Let it not be ſaid of you, That the Lord hath ſmitten your Paſtor, but you have not grieved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Lament your loſs. Do you as yet underſtand what it is? or have you laid it to heart, and yet not pour out tears unto God? I have told you what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally I judg him to be, a Repairer, and an earneſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairer; and if you have found him ſuch an one, O what a loſs do you ſuſtain this day! ye have loſt the company of a Saint, the labours of a painful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a lighter of your Candle, a Champion for your Maſter, the bleſſing of a bleſſed Miniſter, who hath been bleſſed to you, whatever he hath been to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Lament and be humbled for the ſins among you, that thus have provoked the Lord againſt you; ſuch
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65180:16"/>a breach as this may draw tears from the pureſt heart, and the moſt chaſt eye; and ordinarily it's ſuch as are leaſt guilty in this caſe, that mourn moſt. But if thy hand has been againſt this Repairer while at work, and if thy hand hath been upon him to cut him off from the Land of the living; if thy hard heart hath broken his; if thy refuſing to walk in the light, hath provoked God to put out this Candle, and remove this Candleſtick: if thy refuſing to be reconciled, hath made the King call home this Ambaſſador of peace, What great reaſon have you then to lament?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Lament that God hath taken him away before the Word took hold on thy heart and conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou awaked out of thy ſinful ſecurity, before Chriſt was formed within thee by his Miniſtry, before thou was altogether perſuaded to be a Chriſtian; and that now thou art left halting between two, and knows not which to take to; and ſo much the rather, that this is not the firſt Miniſter that hath gone to heaven, and whoſe Funerals you have attended in a Chriſtleſs, graceleſs, hopeleſs, and miſerable condition, which till now thou haſt not laid to heart.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Lament and be humbled that he hath taken him away at ſuch a time when he is threatning many, as <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Then ſaid I, I will not feed you.</hi> Do you not know how many ſeek to deſtroy you this day? Have you not heard that all of us look for a ſtorm, and a ſcattering? one ſuch as that <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. <hi>end?</hi> To ſmite a Shepherd at any time, is ſad; but to take him off when a ſtorm is coming on, is dreadful, as if the ſame Lord had ſaid concerning you, <hi>That which dieth, let it dye; and that that is to be cut off, let it be cut off.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65180:16"/>
               <p n="6">6. Lament over this and the like diſpenſation, as it prognoſticates evil to come, Iſa. 57.1. <hi>The righteous are taken away from the evil to come.</hi> Who knows but by this he may make way to his anger? for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairer is took off his work before breaches be made up, and while there are but few or none to ſtand in the gap to turn away wrath, that he may not deſtroy the Land.</p>
               <p>A ſecond word is of Exhortation, and that in theſe particulars briefly.</p>
               <p>As 1. Truſt not in man, nor in the ſons of men, for wherein are they to be truſted? every one walks in a vain ſhew, and promiſe to ſtay with you a much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time than they can. We appoint bounds to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that we can never come to; for it's not one with his who is the Soveraign determiner of times and ſeaſons; here you ſee one gone to bed at noon-tide of his days, and in the fulneſs of his ſtrength: ceaſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us never give place to ſecurity, but watch and pray always, for we know not in what hour the Son of man will come. Let us ſo walk, that we may be found of him in peace. 3. Let this ſtir all of us up to imitate this Copy in my Text; work while it is to day, for the night cometh; repair, and earneſtly repair, that you may be able to ſtand in the evil day, and finiſh your courſe with joy. Stir up your ſelves, provoke one another to zeal and good works; make ſtraight paths for your feet, leſt that which is lame be turned out of the way, but let it rather be healed. 4. As God hath made you one piece about which he employed the Repairer who is gone, I pray you ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65180:17"/>and ſuffer none to divide one of you from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let none of you ſeek your own things, but the things one of another; and let all of you pray the Maſter builder to ſend you ſuch a bleſſed repairer, as may make you find that he hath turn'd your loſs into gain, and given you a meat-offering and a drink-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a bleſſing</p>
               <p n="3">3. From this you may take a word of reproof; ſuch of you as would not be wrought upon, would not be repaired by this Repairer, ſuch as weakned his hands in his work, ſuch as built againſt him, who were ready to ruine what he repair'd, or who at laſt might be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently inſtrumental in taking him off from his work. As for particular circumſtances, I leave to mens own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; but ſuch would do well to conſider, that it's no ſmall thing to bring a Miniſters, and a bleſſed Miniſters Head to the Grave in ſorrow; that it's yet more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible if thou be one who ought to have been the ſtaff of his old Age; if one whoſe ſoul hath been dear to him as his own; if one from whom honour was due by all the bonds of nature and Religion: it's yet more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible if ſuch in all this ſhould juſtifie themſelves, and harden their heart againſt the Almighty. May not ſuch fear, if they truly repent not, that now when they ceaſe to trouble, they ſhall be troubled? and leſt God cut them off in the midſt of their days? I ſay not this for any other end, but to awaken you, and excite you to repentance. Our Lord is gracious and full of compaſſion, if you ſeek him he will be found of you, he will be gracious at the voice of your cry. If per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons guilty will take hold of Gods ſtrength, that is, his Mercy, we ſhall, for the loſs of one, have many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65180:17"/>
               <p>And now one word more to his afflicted yoke fellow, a copartner with him in all tryals. Now I am left alone. Pray you conſider that you are not alone, for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and chief Repairer is yet with you, and who will never leave you nor forſake you. Ah! the deſire of my eyes is gone. Bleſs God that he died deſired, and that in an acceptable time, in much peace; faint not in your ſighing, but riſe to your work, and the Lord will be with you; remember that there is much of your work to do, let not this aſtoniſh you ſo as to diſable you from duty: put in your claim, lay hold on him for your Husband, Shield and Judge; leave your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs Children on him, let him teach, feed and keep them. In a word, be ſtill knowing that he is God, and hold your peace, knowing not only that he hath done it, but that he will be ſanctified: And make it your buſineſs to know for what he hath ſpared you, and ſet about the doing of it earneſtly till all be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
               <p>That I may cloſe all with a word in general to the multitude. I have been telling you of one repairer in my Text, another in the Providence: I have the beſt of all to tell you off, at the Fathers right hand, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is, and only is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairer: though he makes uſe of our hearts, heads, and hands, and imploys them in doing what is his great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing and reſtoring-work; he it is that makes peace, reſtores to favour and friendſhip with God; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores to life. Now let me perſwade you, if there be any conſolation in Chriſt Jeſus, by the life that you may have in him, by all the promiſes made to you in him, by the life and dying of our Lord Jeſus, by the terrors of God, the torments of Hell, the jaws of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65180:18"/>death, and the comforts of eternal life, let me perſwade you to make choice of Chriſt as your bleſſed Repaires, make uſe of him in repairing, look to him for ſtrength to perform, for acceptance of what you do, and for a bleſſing to make you every way bleſſed. O let none of you dare to follow this Corps, who will not have our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to reign over you</p>
               <p>And to ſay no more, ſeeing by what you have heard you cannot but ſee the riches of Grace which this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Repairer beſtows upon his under-workmen, his Labourers; O! then do as they in <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.8. <hi>But when the multitude ſaw it, they marvelled, and glorified God, which had given ſuch power unto men.</hi> Now you have heard what is in my Text, what you have heard, that you have ſeen many times; Go hence admiring and adoring the bounty and goodneſs of ſuch a one: And by all, be perſwaded to do your work earneſtly, that of you it may be ſaid, as in my Text, <hi>That he repaired earneſtly his piece of the wall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65180:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
